Register of the Poland. Ministerstwo Spraw Zagranicznych Records, 1919-1947.
Hoover Institution Archives
Poland. Ministerstwo Spraw Zagranicznych,
1919-1947.
59003
Poland. Ministerstwo Spraw Zagranicznych. Records
652 manuscript boxes, 10 oversize boxes, 13 envelopes (277 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, bulletins, memoranda, reports, studies, lists, financial records, and photographs, relating to Polish foreign relations during World War II, the Polish government in exile in London, Allied diplomacy during World War II, conditions in Poland during the war, deportation of Poles to the Soviet Union, Polish refugees, the Jewish holocaust in Poland, and Polish military operations. Includes some records of Polish foreign relations during the interwar period. A digital copy of this entire collection is available at http://szukajwarchiwach.pl/800/42/0/-/.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
Alternative Forms of Material Available
Also available on microfilm (541 reels).
Digital copy in Poland's National Digital Archive at http://szukajwarchiwach.pl/800/42/0/-/. It was digitized from microfilm by the Polish State Archives.
Introduction
Now fully organized and provided with a detailed register, the collection of the Polish Foreign Ministry (Poland Ministerstwo Spraw Zagranicznych) at the Hoover Archives constitutes a unique resource for scholars studying not only Polish diplomatic history but the more general subjects of World War II and events surrounding the post-war division of Europe and the beginnings of the Cold War. If for no other reason, the particular status of Poland as victim of both Nazi and Soviet aggression explains the importance of the material in this collection, but it is of renewed interest in light of more recent developments. Five years after the fall of Communism, and with the resulting increased access to East European archives, the historical period covered by the collection has been subjected to a variety of reinterpretations based on newly available records. The collection provides a significant source of primary documentation on a wide range of topics pertinent to such a re-examination.
The history of the collection itself recapitulates many of the events described within its records, and it is directly linked to the fate of independent Poland. Unlike its European counterparts, the Polish state entered the twentieth century without a diplomatic tradition, having endured foreign occupation for more than 100 years. Following the achievement of independence in 1918, it would take many years for the Polish state to establish an official presence on the international level. Before World War II, Poland had still not completed the task of building a comprehensive diplomatic network. As of July 1, 1939, Poland had 10 embassies, 23 legations and 203 consular offices of diverse status throughout the world. This was a level of representation which was not commensurate with the needs of the Polish state.
After the outbreak of World War II with the simultaneous Russian and German invasions of Poland, the government was forced to relocate abroad and reconstruct its operations, including its diplomatic service. In the first months of exile in London, the Foreign Ministry's posts were filled by a new group of officials, who nonetheless were able to maintain a high level of professional competence in the exercise of their duties. Utilizing skilled individuals from among the Polish refugee population, as well as former employees who were smuggled out of occupied Poland, the ministry was able to preserve a clear division of responsibilities within its staff and to sustain an intense diplomatic effort on behalf of Poland. Having been forced to dramatically reduce its diplomatic service at the beginning of the war, the foreign ministry was able to re-establish its representation abroad, so that by the war's end there were some 148 Polish consular offices.
During the war, the Polish government was in the peculiar position of having no territory or subjects to rule and having its armies scattered on different continents. It remained in close touch with occupied Poland and with those who constituted the underground resistance. Each branch of the government in exile had its homologue within occupied Poland, and this kind of parallel operation was unique within occupied Europe. As no puppet governments emerged following the German and Russian invasions, the London government could make sole claim to represent the Polish nation. As part of this representation, it was concerned with preserving the records of the Polish state.
Already in the immediate period prior to the outbreak of hostilities in 1939, the Polish government had been concerned with the selection and transfer of documents from embassies and consulates in countries adjacent to Germany. These materials were sent to Warsaw and became part of the Foreign Ministry archives. Following the invasion of Poland, the ministry was evacuated along with a portion of its archives. Some records were intercepted by German and Russian forces, and a large portion of these has been lost permanently. With London providing a relatively safe environment for governmental activity, the records of the 1940-45 period have survived to a large extent intact, although some records from diplomatic posts abroad were destroyed in the post-war period in an effort to keep them from the new communist authorities in Poland.
The Hoover Archives is in possession of the complete set of the ministry's records covering the years 1939-1944, and some documents from 1945 are to be found within the collection. Supplementing these are the ministry's documents from 1945, which were found in Westminister Cathedral in 1980 and are now housed at the Sikorski Institute in London. Additional records are stored at the Pilsudski Institute in New Jersey. In terms of the size of its Polish Foreign Ministry collection, Hoover is equalled only by the Archiwum Akt Nowych in Warsaw, whose records cover only the inter-war period.
As its name would suggest, the Polish Foreign Ministry collection is especially important in terms of material concerning the history of various policy issues involving the Polish state and other countries. There are some records dating back to independence in 1918, as well as a substantial amount of sensitive material from the entire period before and during World War II, which were marked with the name of the current minister or other government official and kept separate from the rest of the records. For the most part, records of intelligence activities and other classified documents relating to military operations are not found in the collection. Most Polish military activity was under the control of the British, and for that reason records concerning this are generally not available. Material is to be found in the collection at Hoover concerning organizational, as opposed to operational, issues involving the Polish military, such as the formation, training and disposition of Polish forces on Soviet and British territory.
Attention should be drawn to material within the collection which concerns issues of special historical interest. These can be listed by country, region or topic:
THE SOVIET UNION
There is a substantial amount of documents in the collection concerning the Soviet occupation of Poland following the invasion of 1939, as well as its aftermath, including records of the deportation of Poles to the Soviet Union and their subsequent imprisonment or forced resettlement. There are numerous lists of deportees in the papers of the collection, records whose existence was hitherto unknown. The evacuation of former prisoners and the Polish army to the Middle East is also documented, as is the history of the rupture in diplomatic relations between the Soviet Union and Poland. Subsequent political and military agreements between the two countries are also recorded. There is extensive documentation on the formation of the Polish army on Soviet territory and various issues pertaining to this.
EASTERN EUROPE
Polish policies toward various Eastern and Central European countries are documented in the collection, as is the question of Soviet influence and control within these countries before and during World War II. There is significant material concerning Polish relations with Czechoslovakia and Ukraine, Soviet policies toward various nationalities incorporated into the Soviet Union, and general relations between other Eastern European countries and the Soviet Union. German and Soviet intelligence operations in Eastern Europe are also covered.
WESTERN EUROPE/UNITED STATES
There are substantial records in the collection concerning Poland's relations with its allies in World War II, and various shifts in British, French and American policies toward Poland are documented, as are various treaties concluded among the allies. Polish relations with the Vatican are documented, as is Polish participation in various international conferences. There is also a record of the deterioration of relations between Germany and Poland in the immediate pre-war period. While there is documentation of war crimes committed on Polish territory, there is less emphasis on the internal Polish situation than on external issues, military and diplomatic policy, and the organization of the Polish government-in-exile.
WAR CRIMES AND THE DESTRUCTION OF THE JEWS
There is extensive material in the collection concerning both Nazi and Soviet war crimes committed in Poland and elsewhere, as well as documentation concerning the appeals made by the Polish government on behalf of the victims of these actions. Efforts undertaken to save Jews in Poland and elsewhere in occupied Europe are recorded.
REFUGEES AND DISPLACED PERSONS
There is extensive documentation within the collection concerning the fate of Polish refugees and displaced persons within various countries.
Some explanation is necessary of the manner in which the collection is organized. The original system of classification of documents was established by the Polish Foreign Ministry, and this system changed as the ministry underwent a series of reorganizations during the inter-war period. In 1938, in order to facilitate communication with its various representatives, the ministry introduced a uniform index whereby documents were registered and classified. The hierarchies of this system are reflected in the collection itself, with the principal headings being:
1. The internal affairs and foreign policies of other countries
2. Polish relations with other countries
3. International organizations and institutions
4. Special matters, e.g., treaties and religious affairs
5. Emigration and the status of Poles abroad
6. Press and propaganda
7. Transportation
8. The internal structure of the foreign ministry and the organization of its diplomatic service
9. Consular issues
10. Polish internal affairs
In this system of classification, 200 numbers were left "empty," being available to be used for additional categories, which is in fact what happened during World War II. These numbers are maintained in the present organization of the collection, although some series do not appear due to a loss of documents prior to Hoover's acquisition of the collection. In some cases, material on the same subject may be found under more than one category due to an overlap in the general topic, as in the case of an issue affecting several countries or several departments within the Polish government. For example, the care of Polish refugees was the responsibility of the Ministry of Labor and Social Welfare, as well as the Foreign Ministry. Researchers interested in a particular topic are advised to search under other similar categories.
The Foreign Ministry Collection has been reduced in size over time, as many individual collections (from embassies and consulates), which did not originate from the Foreign Ministry itself, have been separated out from the main body of the documents. During the present reorganization of the collection, several of these separate series were identified, two of the most important being the collections of the Polish Legation to the Czechoslovak Government in London and the Polish Embassy in Dublin. The latter collection also contains material from the post-war period. Other, smaller collections (for the most part consisting individually of one box of material) include that of the Polish consulate in Lille, France and those of the following Polish embassies: Kuibyshev, London, Paris, Rome, Budapest, Bucharest, Belgrade, Copenhagen, Hague, Brussels, the League of Nations. These supplement already established collections in the Hoover Archives from other Polish embassies and consulates.
The bulk of the Foreign Ministry Collection is comprised of correspondence, telegrams, memoranda, minutes, clippings, statements of protocol and printed matter. Photographs constitute a separate file within the collection. The present work of organizing the collection began with a sequential rearrangement of all the folders, a process which restored the original series established by the Foreign Ministry. Much of the material had remained untouched from the time of its shipment to Hoover and had to be removed from its original file covers. The documents are grouped by series, which are subdivided chronologically and by individual categories, according to the importance of the material. This detailed classification allows for the ready indentification of thousands of names, organizations and subjects; it should also enhance the accessibility of eventual microfilm copies of the collection. It should be stressed, however, that the index to the register of the collection refers to the headings on the folders, not to their entire contents.
Until 1991, the collection was used by researchers in the form in which it had been originally shipped to Hoover. Following the current reorganization of the collection, a list of the previous numbering (of folders and boxes) has been preserved. It may be found in the last box of the collection.
The vast majority of the documents in this collection is in Polish, although some are in French and English. Variations in geographic place names reflect changes in borders, as in the case of Polish territory annexed by the Soviet Union, as well as changes in usage. The particularities of Polish orthography (characters and accents) have been omitted from the present register.
In the final stages of preparing the register of this collection, I was assisted by the efforts of others in editing the index and with general clerical support. My thanks go especially to Linda Bernard, who contributed months of work on the index. Others to whom I am grateful are Karen Horrigan, David Jacobs, Anne Kvittum, Carol Leadenham, Andrew Olah, Natasha Porfirenko, Dale Reed, and Dina Updegraff.
Access Points
Poland. Polskie Sily Zbrojne.; Poles in foreign countries.; World War, 1939-1945.; World War, 1939-1945--Deportations from Poland.; World War, 1939-1945--Diplomatic history.; World War, 1939-1945--Governments in exile.; World War, 1939-1945--Poland.; Poland.; Poland--Foreign relations.; Poland--History--Occupation, 1939-1945.; Refugees.; Holocaust, Jewish (1939-1945); Jews--Poland.; Soviet Union.; Russia (Federation)
FILE LIST (ENGLISH)
Only the series numbers listed in bold or italics are available at the Hoover; series numbers not listed in bold or italics are not extant and thus not available at the Hoover.
CHAPTER ONE: FOREIGN COUNTRIES
POLITICAL CONDITIONS ABROAD
1 Foreign relations of various countries, not involving Poland
2 Ministry's instructions
3 Political reports
4 ["Empty" classification number]
5 ["Empty" classification number]
6 ["Empty" classification number]
INTERNAL AFFAIRS OF VARIOUS COUNTRIES
7 Political system, government, parliament
8 Political parties
9 Organizations and political associations
10 Political emigration
11 Nationalist and separatist movements
12 Communist movements
13 Minorities outside Poland's borders
14 Colonial policy
15 Cultural and educational relations
16 Federations
17 Panslavism
18 ["Empty" classification number]
19 Economic relations of various countries, not involving Poland
20 Economic affairs of colonies, protectorates, mandate countries
21 Finances and credits
a/general conditions
b/banks
c/valorization
22 Industry
a/general conditions
b/banks
c/valorization
22 Industry
23 Agriculture
24 Mining
25 Forestry
26 Minerals /raw materials/
27 Multinational cartels with participation of various countries
28 Trade
a/domestic
b/foreign
29 Social issues
30 Agrarian reform
31 Labor market
32 Job availability for foreigners
33 Population
a/increase
b/decrease
c/emigration
d/immigration
34 Settlement
35 Foreign colonization organizations
36 Economic institutions
37 Economic situation in general
38 Ministry instructions
39 Economic reports
40 Biuro Prac Ekonomicznych (Bureau of Economic Studies)
41 Komisja Zaopatrzenia Kraju (Commission for State Provision)
42 ["Empty" classification number]
43 ["Empty" classification number]
44 ["Empty" classification number]
45 ["Empty" classification number]
46 German credits for frontier regions
47 Product dumping
CHAPTER TWO: RELATIONS OF POLISH REPUBLIC WITH OTHER COUNTRIES
POLITICAL RELATIONS
48 Instructions of Ministry
49 Political relations with Poland in general
50 Propaganda on specific political issues
51 Grievances and compensations settled through diplomatic channels
a/anti-semitic campaign in Germany
b/compensation law
52 Political reports
53 Name index (instructions)
54 Maritime affairs
55 Issues related to military occupation
ECONOMIC RELATIONS
56 Instructions of Ministry
57 Economic relations with Poland in general
58 Poland's war debts
59 Trade turnover regulation
60 Product certificates
61 Polish capital and Polish enterprises abroad
62 Foreign capital and enterprises in Poland
63 International producers agreement
64 Polish coal
65 Customs duties
a/customs tariffs
b/customs law
c/information, complaints, mediation
d/customs duty increase
e/customs duty offices
66 Markets for Polish trade products
67 Veterinary and phytopathological issues
68 Trade conferences
69 Chambers of commerce
a/in Poland
b/abroad
70 Publicity in economic affairs
71 Economic conditions in Poland
72 ["Empty" classification number]
73 Political conditions in Poland
a/German ocupation zone
b/Soviet occupation zone
74 Post-war planning
AGREEMENTS: BI- AND MULTILATERAL
75 Political agreements
76 Military agreements
77 Conciliation and arbitration agreements
78 Legal agreements
a/legal assistance in civil law
b/legal assistance in penal law
c/extraditions
d/issuance of court sentences
e/execution of court sentences
f/international property law
79 Consular agreements
80 Passport agreements
81 General economic agreements
82 Commercial and customs agreements
83 Financial agreements
84 Agricultural agreements
85 Insurance and labor agreements
86 Emigration and repatriation agreements
87 Citizenship agreements
88 Settlement agreements
89 Liquidation agreement
90 Scientific agreements
91 Legal documents agreements
92 Sanitary and veterinary agreements
93 Border agreements
94 Transportation agreements
95 Railway agreements
96 Maritime agreements
97 Aviation agreements
98 Fluvial agreements
99 Inland navigation-ship measurement agreements
100 Road transport agreements
101 Motor transport agreements
102 Transit agreements
103 Exchange of diplomatic valises
104 Tourist agreements
105 Postal agreements
106 Telegraphic agreements
107 Radiotelegraphic agreements
108 Statistical agreements
109 Fishing agreements
110 Agreements concluded without Poland's participation
111 International agreements concluded by Poland on behalf of Gdansk
112 Cultural agreements
113 ["Empty" classification number]
114 Ratification of agreements
CHAPTER THREE: INTERNATIONAL ORGANIZATIONS AND INSTITUTIONS
VATICAN
115 Vatican's foreign relations (excluding Poland)
116 Central organs of the Catholic Church
117 Functioning of central offices
118 Catholic movement
119 ["Empty" classification number]
120 ["Empty" classification number]
121 ["Empty" classification number]
122 Vatican's relations with Poland. Concordat
123 ["Empty" classification number]
124 ["Empty" classification number]
LEAGUE OF NATIONS
125 Sessions
126 Council
a/elections
127 Secretariat
a/budget
b/personnel of Secretariat
c/Polish officials in League of Nations
d/trips of secretariat officials to Poland
e/Polish publications for League of Nations Library
f/documents and publications of League of Nations
g/registration of agreements with League of Nations
h/agreements supervised by League of Nations
WARRANTS OF INTERNATIONAL SECURITY
128 Security agreements
129 Committee for Arbitrage and Security
130 Standing Advisory Committee on Military Affairs
131 Disarmament Conference
132 Maritime Conference
133 Armaments
134 European Advisory Committee
135 International Armistice Committee
136 Allied Forces Committee of Foreign Affairs Ministers
POLITICAL AND ECONOMIC AFFAIRS
137 a/Reorganization of League of Nations
b/Relations of various nations within League of Nations
138 Conflicts between League of Nations members
139 International economic cooperation under auspices of League of Nations
a/League of Nations Economic Committee
b/League of Nations Financial Committee
c/League of Nations Public Works Committee
d/European Studies Committee
e/International Exchange of Economic Statistics
f/World Economic Conference
g/Agricultural Bloc
h/International Agreement on Forestry
i/International Agreement on Grain
j/International Agreement on Coal
140 Social assistance
141 League of Nations Finance Committee
142 European Studies Committee
143 Economic statistics
144 Mandates
LEGAL ISSUES
145 Pact amendments
146 Pact interpretations
147 Revisionist procedure in League of Nations Pact
148 ["Empty" classification number]
149 ["Empty" classification number]
TECHNICAL OPERATIONS
150 Advisory and Technical Commission on Transit and Communication
151 Communication and Transit
152 Organization of hygiene
153 Intellectual cooperation
154 Straits Commission
155 League of Nations commissions
156 ["Empty" classification number]
157 Welfare work
158 Slave trade and child welfare
159 Immoral publications
160 Slavery
161 Prevention against abuse of intoxicants
162 Legal assistance for impoverished
163 Organization of international assistance
164 Repatriation. International organizations of refugee assistance
165 ["Empty" classification number]
166 ["Empty" classification number]
INTERNATIONAL TRIBUNALS AND COMMISSIONS
167 International tribunals. Organizational matters
168 Disputes before Mieszany Trybunal Rozjemczy Polsko-Niemiecko Gornoslaski (Polish-German Upper Silesian Mediation Tribunal)
169 Disputes before Mieszana Komisja Gornoslaska (Mixed Upper-Silesian Commission)
170 International Court of Justice in The Hague
171 Mediation Standing Court in The Hague
172 Matters of Conciliation Commission in Locarno
173 Disputes before Mediation Court
174 Mediterranean Commission /Council/
175 ["Empty" classification number]
176 ["Empty" classification number]
INTERNATIONAL LABOUR OFFICE
177 Organization and personnel
178 Activities
179 International labor conventions
180 ["Empty" classification number]
181 ["Empty" classification number]
182 ["Empty" classification number]
INTERNATIONAL INSTITUTES AND BUREAUS
183 International institutes and bureaus
INTERNATIONAL CONGRESSES, CONFERENCES AND MEETINGS
184 International congresses, conferences and meetings
INTERNATIONAL BANKS
185 Bank for International Settlements
186 ["Empty" classification number]
187 ["Empty" classification number]
188 ["Empty" classification number]
INTERNATIONAL SCIENTIFIC RELATIONS
SCIENTIFIC ACTIVITIES
189 Polish scholarly institutions abroad and foreign institutions in Poland